[Music]
I really I really loved your book by the
way and I thought it was very beautiful
very eloquent and I really like the I
like the combination of this very
intimate personal observations with sort
of philosophy and and high abstraction
and yeah the book was really for me an
attempt to see the experience as a whole
the becoming a young chess player and
being highly driven to win so develop
miss strong competitive urge which was
also by advancement and identity and
personal growth and then at some point
partly through becoming a father partly
through just growing up you know began
beginning to realize there were other
ways some of your life you know that it
wasn't just about your next competitive
victory yeah so that was the book in
some ways is making sense of those
different impulses on the one hand the
natural competitive urge to win and
being all that yeah then sort of saying
goodbye to it as well so yeah what is
that there's this kind of paradox in
your character right this just being
extremely hyper competitive and almost
warrior like and actually what really
matters to you is is kids the more
carrying aspect of of life on some level
possibly yeah so as you probably know
you know the warrior archetype type is
partly about a kind of sublimation it's
partly about
finding something that's worth living
for and focusing all your energy on that
and mobilizing and as it's more for that
end so that that spirit of you know
single-minded attention I you know I've
got a lot of respect for a lot I see it
in people I I see its power
I see how it can forge great progress
I see how it can cut through a lot of
noise you know I admire it and I think
it's a necessary energy in the world I
also think there's more to life and
something somewhere along the way
that ceased to make as much sense to me
that desire I remember one time being in
a hotel room in Spain and I mentioned
this in the booth and just sort of
trying to sort of get ready for the next
game
trying to find that warrior who wanted
to win and wanted to win the tournament
and beat the guy next and I just noticed
that that wasn't me anymore I still
respected it I could still justify
pretend to be that person but I began to
think there are bigger battles to be
fought in one so do you think being a
full-on warrior has more to do with the
grace of learning how to lose up in some
sense or learning how to be broken or
learning how to lose gracefully because
none of us sort of rise to the extreme
you know image of ourself well become
the divine double there's a word that
John for Vicky was using and so we
always fall short of that aren't on a
human level and becoming human in some
sense has to do with failure as much as
is right yes so there's as you probably
know in the book the moves of Master
there was a little bit of a nasty heroic
side to it it's partly about me coming
to terms with the fact that I was never
going to be world champion and I didn't
really ever try or ever have a very
serious chance at that but there were
many moments of inflection when after a
particularly big tournament or a great
run I might have got ideas that oh maybe
I can go all the way but at some point
you kind of reach your limitations you
play people and you know that that was
no accident that you lost that game you
know you may learn you may play a bit
better next time but there are clear
limitations and I think that's true in
almost any dimension of life you know
better philosophers better activists
better fathers you know I think it's
it's something about growing up that you
you come to appreciate your strengths
and weaknesses and get to know yourself
a bit better as a result for me in chess
it was something about letting go of
that ultimate desire to be more easy
with what had happened right
is it also something to do with
at one point deciding to let go of being
a specialist in one field I know in my
20s I wanted to be a songwriter it was
like I was driven to that it was the
only thing I cared about and then at one
point I I came to the realization that
you know I you know I got married and I
all these other things happen to me
which made it impossible to be so one
pointedly devoted to that one goal and
my life became more diverse and rich but
but I I couldn't concentrate on that one
thing to the degree that I I wanted to
so is that yes that's very pertinent
because it reminds me of the quotation I
think by Joseph Campbell you know you
asked which myth are you living by yeah
and I think in the case of my younger
self this single pointed attention this
mobilized the will and the heart of the
soul of the mind to get as good as
possible at this one thing chess and
that was very much part of the story it
was about let me show the world that I
can focus let me show the world that I
can dedicate myself to this through
discipline and there's a lot of self
love in that for good and bad you know
there was a sort of genuine discipline
information of character with you know
without chess that wouldn't have
happened another hand you know that
monomania that sense that a I was really
important being the game is really
important and see the next game and the
next move really mattered these were all
kind of part of a myth you know and at
some point you're getting to realize
you're telling the story of yourself and
there are other ways of telling that
story so yes marriage was part of it
doing you know my educational activities
was part of the chess was always a kind
of plan B even when I didn't really have
a plan a you know it was like I didn't
know what planning it was yet but I just
knew that chess wasn't it it was more
like what I was doing when it wasn't
doing something else interesting I was
thinking as you were talking about my
recent discussion with with Zack and
John and we talked about this notion of
the divine double and towards the end of
the conversation
Zach was mentioning that the divine
double is multiple it's not it's not
just one it's us you're not just one
person you're many different people
you're many different archetypes that
you're trying to become and they're
often in conflict with each other
absolutely so maybe when you're younger
you're focused towards just that one and
then when you get older you you you have
this you have a wider view of all right
so I mean we did you know I think that's
that sign is roughly right and um I
actually watched that conversation and I
know that quite well and the notion of
the psyche is clurel is worth just
taking a while to sit with because it's
plural in several different ways like
speaking in quite a sort of archetypal
maybe post Union kind of way yeah um and
he's trying to say that I think once you
go into the into the psyche more deeply
you find that there are these competing
energies and then the question is well
who is observing them who's mediating
between them is there such a thing is
the self just that conversation between
your for example your warrior your
wizard your your dysfunctional child
your you know whatever else your
masculine and feminine that's be even
more basically your consumer and your
shopper and your cleaner and you know
the past the parts of you that are not
so you know exalted or mysterious yeah
and they're all kind of battling it out
to be who you are and sometimes it feels
like the right version of yourself
prevails and sometimes it doesn't
you know and but what was what was there
what what where think Zach and John's
conversation was going at least that's
where my mind was taking it was um
there's this question of the witness you
know who is observing this plural psyche
mm-hmm does it make sense is the psyche
just floral is it are we merely a
conversation or is there a sense in
which someone's witnessing that
conversation or something Nora all right
this got me intrigued you know
well I remember the the mystic kerchief
says man is legion but he also said
there should be one sort of central
controller who's looking at those other
multiple personalities and and is in
control and saying you should do this or
you shouldn't buy this otherwise we get
swept away all right we can and yeah
Boston accounts true true on yet that
looks looks scarier they like a kind of
old-fashioned review of a Cartesian cell
with in Jakarta right so I think the
view I think it might be more mystical
than that it might be that those
archetypal cells that are somehow in our
psyche conversing among themselves
competing and collaborating in various
ways I suspect the holding pattern for
them is something transpersonal it may
even be spirit in some sense or there
are lots of words for it being or you
know God or you know but something
that's not merely personality but you
want something to be on the personality
right that seems very important that it
seems to me that we that there's a need
to connect with that in the modern times
where we're so obsessed with personality
or so ups you know yeah so I mean I I
with the you mentioned a spiritual eyes
boom I think my favorite single line
perhaps there were several about what
spirituality is was from the Buddhist
psychoanalyst mark Epstein and he says
spirituality is whatever it takes you
beyond the personality yeah I find that
quite astute and it stayed with me a
little bit hmm
because I guess the personality you can
develop it you can develop it a lot but
it still remains a prison if you don't
go beyond that on some level yeah and
the most beautiful is I mean I can't
speak from personal experience as such
but I think somewhere in my book I also
mentioned this there's a quite a well
well-worn line that says you have to be
somebody before you can be nobody mmm
the contention is that some ourself has
to be constructed and coherent for some
extent before it's needed yeah and if
you go straight towards deconstruction
you just have this chaos and and I think
that line is good but what what a little
twist on it I think is that you find
that when you meet the nobodies were the
advanced spiritual practitioners that
the people considered wise yeah and they
actually have radiant personalities
it's just that it's sort of not
self-consciously held anymore it's sort
of it's it's there but it's no longer
it's no longer a project you know it's
no longer fear-based review based and
it's not great it's not trying it's not
adapting to the world not they're not
using this personality as a kind of tool
to filter out experience it's more like
once they've gone beyond the need to do
that they still show up with their own
quirks and yeah you know yeah so at the
risk of sounding sentimental it's it
everything I guess the most developed
being would be the one who is just at
service to the world in in love if I
could say that yeah well quiet although
like you say the risk of sentimentality
you know where you know where are we
with that because I'm yeah I find myself
wanting to say things like love is a
fundamental significance find out what
you can serve and so forth but then we
live in such a self-conscious culture
that I also think well that sounds a bit
worthy you know yeah and love has such a
kind of gross when we talk about love it
has a sentimental flavor to it whereas
there's a fierceness to it there's a
directness to it there's you know
there's a softness there's both aspects
like yes yes doesn't have to be
sentimental or sappy or no formal sense
that I I mean or in the sense of the
person you're talking about who has
embodied that you know I mean I think
love properly understood is that which
brings us to tears you know I think it's
the feeling we have when we sense we've
given our all and you know
they grateful and these kind of feelings
of self overcoming but I'm also reminded
of the beautiful quotation by Martin
Luther King about love and power you
probably know it but you know in essence
he speaks about the problem with the
world being that we've we've defined an
undershoot power to be either the
absence of love and and love to be the
absence of power as if there were
somehow pull their opposites didn't he
call it soul power or something like
that yeah possibly that made me
somewhere else but but he has a famous
quotation I didn't spiritual eyes and I
might even a my even if put it in the
mousse that matter because I liked it so
much but he just says the challenge of
our time is bringing love and power
together hmm and figuring out what that
means and it's an ongoing project but
it's it is about what does it mean to
love and serve the world at the moment
whereas yeah sorry to interrupt I
thought that might be a good segue to
talk about your let's say your activism
or your interest in kind of bringing
bringing spirituality into politics
uh-huh
so I want to ask you about that partly
because it's a weakness
in my own life is that I I tend to be
apolitical and I tend to think that's a
weakness of my mind and maybe you can
help me with that how do I have a
spiritual how do we bring spirituality
into actual like political action well
I've been thinking about this for at
least five years now and the first thing
I would say is that I fight I think
without without wanting to finesse the
term too much and having used the word
spirituality for several years I began
to realize there was something
problematic not about the reference to
the spiritual not about a spiritual
practice or spiritual experience or even
spiritual knowledge or beliefs but
spirituality as a complex composite nine
he's actually a deeply problematic term
it's misleading yeah you say
spirituality you're placing it in the
world of tables and chairs as a thing
that exists in the world with its own
objective reality it also has a Gnostic
flavor doesn't it it's dividing spirit
from matter or right there's that food
and then and people get consumed some
breathing people get concerned about it
because it they're concerned about
spiritualism and spirits and
metaphysical features of the term so the
first thing they say is that I tend
these days to refer to spiritual
sensibility and the challenge of
cultivating that what does it mean to
have spiritual sensibility and by that I
mean a kind of feature of how we are
disposed to be and to one extent that we
push our inquiry to the the you know our
cosmological framework as a whole our
deepest values are strongest and most
resonant experiences so when I say
spiritual sensibility I mean a kind of
feature of how we relate to the world
and I don't think that kind of
sensibility isn't any sense
controversial although although is
required so have spiritual sensibility
is to be interested in the meaning of
life yeah to be interested in the
cultivation of virtue and to be
interested in the nature of reality yeah
and most people have these things it's
just that at any given moment we happen
to greater or lesser extent but religion
seems to be the thing that's problematic
these days I mean right right so yes and
when I was doing the spirituality
project it was an anthropologists called
Matthew angle in the room in one of our
workshops and I'll never forget the
moment where we were floundering around
with definitions and you know what is it
about spiritual and my spirituality why
is it a problem and he says well guys
the word spiritual has a history and
that history has a politics hmm and this
is art of a matter of spirituality is
closely related to religion which is
deeply political and historical and
so we've come a bit off the original
question so let me try and weave this
back to that okay by the relationship
between the spiritual and the political
it's like this if you without getting
too deep into the diagnosis of the world
we have a certain kind of political
economy in advanced Western world we
have a certain kind of social imaginary
which is something to do with
consumerism and individualism and
personal freedom and ownership
it's about nation-state it's about legal
systems you know we have certain notions
of what's normal
yeah and we've also gone through a
historical period where we decided that
the ideological battle was somehow won
and the and that liberal democratic
capitalism broadly conceived was somehow
the answer the end of history right so I
sometimes even joke on the end of
history that were all fukuyama's
children right I also mean that I'm you
and I and many people sort of similar
age grew up thinking that we may have
reached the end of history or at least
at least that was a condemned at least
it was a possibility I'm not sure I ever
really bought it but clearly that's not
the case today well also can I just
interject also we have we've gone
through post-modernism which has been a
critique of everything so we believe but
we don't believe there's a kind of like
there's a modern project and then Jack
calls it the I think he called the book
tragic tragic yeah yeah yeah well so
yeah there's too much to talk about but
the way I we we ever try and complete
the initial point is that um what change
really was waking up to the influence of
ecology technology and finance and we
could get lost in that but in essence
logical constraints ecological collapse
finance sort of subverting and we think
of the economy and your kind marketing
version is like the market stall where
people are trading goods and services
and some are getting prosperous and some
are having their needs met right that's
you're gonna fool capitalism yeah but
what we have today is something more
like surveillance extractive
kleptocratic plutocratic data-driven
inequality driving socially corrosive
capitalism right not necessarily the
underlying logic of the market is
problematic it's something about what
this beast has become and then on top of
that you have the influence of
technology which is implicated in both
ecology and in finance but in essence
technology is now changing within
generations rather than just between
them so you have these these stabilizing
influences right and in that context it
feels like the modernist project the
project that said look we'll have
nation-states will have a free market
the individual has certain rights well
have private property every will be
alright go about your business right
that world is sort of broken but no one
that's free has been proven to be
inadequate yeah especially today with
coronavirus oh my god I mean I don't
want to bring that in too much but but
that seems to be giving us a view of our
limitations on all levels it's like so
it is incredible and Karuna I'm happy to
come to that a second that is definitely
a reckoning yeah the reckoning though
prior to that even just you know look
closely the climate science and what
it's asking of us politically and you
realize it's going to be extremely
difficult to avoid much worse ecological
cascading a lot right right look closely
at the fact that the tech giants from
Silicon Valley are now so powerful that
in effect the public realm was now
controlled by private actors well and
then look closely at how how finance
serves the democratic system
keeps perpetuating it in the way things
are funded now none of these points I
hasten to add are coming from a
particularly socialistic communistic
perspective mmm coming from someone who
you know I'm fairly political but to be
honest I couldn't really care who gets
elected tomorrow or the next day yeah
little more like I want people to be
kind of sane and less deluded and I
think there's a lot of delusion baked
into the system so when you ask me in a
word of this virtue I'll have to come in
it comes in about getting beyond
systemic delusion sort of see into the
problems of the world but it's also by
renewal so it's about where the
resources conceptual experiential solar
istic relational imaginative resources
going to come from to survive and thrive
for the next 100 years and beyond
they're gonna come from deep places
right indeed crusted places and they'll
be spiritual and to some extent
religious - yeah all I was I was
thinking that I was thinking that people
are talking about the end of religion I
feel like we're at the beginning of
religion in some level well this is
interesting because I may be using this
have kind of evolved as I've grown up
about six or seven years ago when I back
began the spirituality project at the
Royal Society of Arts of London and just
to give a bit of context that's a
relatively conventional enlightenment
organisation and biking vengeful I mean
that and sort of an intellectual
cultural sense it's kind of a cutting
edge of the establishment but still the
establishment yeah and it's also fairly
rationalistic and even a bit
technocratic and in that context I
managed to raise the funds to create
this project on rethinking spirituality
on the basis of new understandings of
human nature the human beings are
significantly more socialized
significantly more automatic
sufficiently more significantly more
embodied than we previously thought and
by that I mean cognition is not not
deliberative and
it's something much more about an
organism trying to get by his group and
achieve his goals and so forth all of
which to say these new theories about
what the human being is I thought should
change our idea of what spiritual life
was a back and at that time I could fast
I did that because I thought religion
was on the way I and yang's I thought
like all of this old fashion of the gym
are absurd and quaint it seems now
mm-hmm but then I had a bit of a you
know a transformative set of encounters
with lots of people some very divided
Christians became very close friends for
example my wife's for the joy White's
him Indian and Hindu right um I began to
look at that differently as a result too
intellectually and relatively Buddhist
the books I'm drawn to her a bit more
about understanding the finer points of
experience in the mind yeah and then
because of with the university for about
seven or eight years I'm quite skeptical
you don't quite know I'm not ticklin
credulous I want to so that mixture of
experiences made me think a little bit
differently about religion namely that
you know we have this this extraordinary
historical gift yeah these resources and
traditions and institutions and
practices and the idea that that's all
kind of old-fashioned hogwash yeah you
know immature as hell well I feel that's
immature I was listening to this rabbi
on YouTube that my life my wife likes to
listen to and he was talking about
following the Torah and I was thinking
about how difficult that must be like
what what a challenge it is to follow a
religious like a religious path you know
deeply and we're almost too superficial
to do this or I shouldn't say we but the
average North American or European we
think we're so intelligent and wise and
advanced but we couldn't possibly follow
the Torah you know anyway so there's
this extreme depth that comes along with
following a religious path
you know fully and I very much have a
lot doing that even though I try to you
know but irony irony of that I think is
that before you look too closely at it
it can look as if the barrier to entry
to experiences and practices and give me
community and tradition it's sort of
surrendering your intellect right it can
look to some people like alright I kind
of like your community I quite like your
songs I might even have a bit of your
wine but don't give me any of that Jesus
rose on the third day stuff right yeah
but once you get to know the people a
bit better and spend a bit more time
there you realize they're not that hung
up on the beliefs you know it's not it
comes into a more permeating set of
experiences in which those beliefs begin
to be a bit more resonant and meaningful
but it's not as if everything's driven
by them at least not in the more liberal
churches that I observed but I could
also say it also appears that there's a
lot of dead religion out there that's
just just propositional and and dogmatic
and unbearable and nice so I think
living religion I mean I when I said
religion is gonna come back I I don't
mean that in a positive sense I mean
that is like it's both right
cultish spirit seems to be what will
arise in all of this chaos that yeah
well now but also also different
communities of sense-making and but
since making is you don't like that word
I was your word for sense making I was
trying to remember what it was there was
no it's funny the second person today to
tell me I don't like that term must be
somehow out there but I'm it was
intelligibility I I kind of knew yeah
the chat we had a challenge of at
intelligibility today to make to make
sense of the world world but when people
turn it into sense making you know good
luck to them is fine it's not my concern
we babbling a little peoples languages
but um
for me sense making sounds a bit funny
that's a bit intellectual it sounds a
bit like Oh yellow we'll just do this
and do this and we'll make sense and
that's gonna yeah it turns it makes it
sound like you practice and I guess I'm
I don't mean to be convinced that it
really is a practice perhaps it could be
brass I just don't have the experiences
that sense making process properly
understood may be worthy of that name
I haven't yet experienced it yet oh yeah
but I don't know if I answered your
original original question fully but um
the way guys sorry you're just say that
I'm in terms of whether religions coming
back it's tricky right because it
depends on who you were talking to you
and how old they are what they've been
through
for some people religion is still a big
allergy you know it's still a religious
people still means a potentially
coercive source of authority who will
take away your freedom
and what I realized quite recently
actually and this this is where the two
worlds intersect a little bit
the term spirituality sometimes even
called spiritual but not religious yeah
and the thing that's interesting about
that is it's an absurd expression right
it's like being healthy but not medical
or you know learning but not through
education or something on that and it's
got this kind of deinstitutionalized
feel to it well I guess we need to
define what religion means like to us
and and what it really means you know
rather than just being Christianity or
Islam or you know what is Russell really
mean I mean yeah I mean you have other
authorities there you have you know
relieve you when I heard Zack and John
speaking about that before
really you open meaning sort of the bind
together or the need for communal
practices which which lifts up the
spirit and lifts the spirit also gives
you a kind of commitment device and
reinforced with discipline and give you
a whole point and renew your renew your
commitment
that give you a certain tempo to
existence that structures your time and
attention that gives you clarity of
purpose yeah is your social support you
know lots of things about religion are
fabulous and if you don't have that it
you have a perverted version of that
right often are usually or maybe always
right it can manifest in other ways but
here's the point I wanted to make it is
it's a it's a point I haven't really
articulated public courses where it's
getting it right but it's like this why
is it that some people are so allergic
to the term spirituality there were
several reasons but there's one that I
would add which is that spirituality is
really liberalism to tenants to have a
spiritual life without yeah it's it's
liberalism's way of saying we can have
all the good stuff that you mentioned
all the good experiences yeah without
the commitment without the commitment
without the police based activities
without the family and community
commitment without the service we're
gonna do the stuff that we enjoy is
we're free agents and we can greater
like everyone that's interesting because
that's all bound up in the Protestant
the whole Protestant notion of just you
can make it up as you go along or you
can have a direct relationship to God
and you can have it all right you don't
lose the church you don't really
doctrine you don't need I'm on you know
even more on the edge of my competence
than unusual but on the theology I I
couldn't be sure but I imagine there are
those who would say that one of the
things that makes Protestant
Protestantism thus faint is that it's
there's a kind of sense making capacity
can refer it on the agent but it's not
completely untethered from institutional
support or practice or beauty but maybe
in its in it's pathological form maybe
it has a very good aspect to it the
self-critical aspect but it is in
pathological format it leads to a kind
of do-it-yourself spirituality consumer
spirituality where you just get a bunch
of techniques and you you stitch them
together and any patchwork that you like
and then you have a nice
but they're you don't go very deep right
so here's here's where this point needs
to be understood fully I think because
and when I was a bit younger I would
have thought well what's wrong with that
you know like pick-and-mix great I'll
have an eclectic view why can't I take
the best of the best and why can I trust
myself to forge it and build my own life
around it mhm
so that's a good question and then you
say to them well Luke that is the
essence of much of the liberal project
that's a blank slate ideology isn't it I
mean well it's not just a blank slate I
guess the point I'm making is that
there's a connection between the
individual desire to do that and
liberalism's
failure and by that I mean these
problems I mentioned earlier of
Technology controlling the public realm
private actors controlling the public
realm cascading ecological collapse and
kind of financial overreach in every
aspect of our life leading to socially
corrosive inequality democratic
breakdown and so forth those are all
liberalism's watch right and so when the
person says I want to do these things
that's still caught up in the liberalist
liberal is sort of liberal imaginary
it's still caught up in this idea that
somehow being free in the private realms
of private agent to create your own
spiritual life is absolutely fine
because that's how we do things now yeah
the myth of the thing not working right
but the answer is it's not working very
well it's destroying society it's
destroying the social fabric it doesn't
mean there's nothing in it it doesn't
mean you go back to old-time religion
and listen to the minister yeah but it
doesn't mean think twice the question is
maybe yeah so so how do you how do you
how do you have a spiritual or let's say
religious life in the in the 21st
century that's kind of your question
isn't it
question really is how do we bring
matters the fundamental concern to bear
on in the public realm in a way that can
make his publisher you know well but
that word program is often used to avoid
politics I guess I mean in a way that
has a bearing on or the design of public
policy and so to give you an example
there's a big debate within economics
about whether economic growth is
sustainable and whether in order to you
know cope on a finite planet some
believe that we can progressively make
economic production cleaner with green
energy and renewable materials and that
actually the they build the sort of the
growth grouse them growth the met sorry
the gross domestic product yeah the
perpetuation and continued growth of GDP
gross domestic product is possible and
that we and not only is it possible but
it's sort of essential so the green
growth advocates and that actually that
theory to some extent is the basis for
the greening deal which is a big
political in the US and I don't based on
growth mm-hmm right nobody some growth
and and it gets to the question of what
exactly is going on there what is this
growth doing spiritually what sense is
it conferring reality on something in
what sense does it make us feel real or
make life meaningful do we actually need
it and the reason that question matter
is is that I think when you look at the
best models and Tim Jackson I'm
associated with a a university center
here at the University of Surrey called
the Center for the understanding of
sustainable prosperity and the argument
we have is not it's not an T grows again
it's not coming from a place of bring
down these terrible capitalists and
saying look look at the data look at the
evidence it appears that there are
there's a strong connection between one
particular kind of economic growth and
ecological degradation this is we've
known this for a long time it's
continuing the link is there to what
extent can you decouple them right and
the debate goes that there's no doubt
you can decouple it in a relative sense
so that every gaming unit is a bit
cleaner and a bit better than the
previous one but there is a big argument
over whether you can reduce it in an
absolute sense and decouple it such that
in the globe as a whole we can carry on
growing and reduce for instance
emissions especially carbon emissions
okay let's go back to coronavirus then
maybe cuz you don't mind and you just
you're sure excuse me I'm just because
it's necessary to make the problem with
the work that I do and work a lot of the
people you speak to do is to connect
sort of disciplines and paradigms and
contexts yeah and epistemologies takes a
bit of time right because you've gotta
unpack the stall and go the world's and
then you forge a relationship then you
analyze the relationship but in this
case I'm just saying that if you take
the growth of the bank it would appear
that the argument will be foreign one of
the level of persuasive policy reasoning
like this for this if we have green
girls will have this number of jobs we
have you know you lower emissions and
this will be a good policy outcome right
yeah if you have a more existential
level about what are you actually living
for what is the good Society what is the
good life right it's very far from clear
that the growth model is the way that's
not even in a part of the discussion is
like it's just about it's just about
let's say a building an engineering the
utopia right and it's not it's not about
what's the meaning of this of our lives
like mmm-hmm and people I assume if you
just build the Utopia then we'll just
all figure out what the meaning of life
is but I feel like even though there's a
coronavirus I'm in a nice little house
in the in a French village and I'm
totally in a utopia right but you know I
still have struggles
sorry to make it personal I just mean
let's come to the personal the
existential it matters it matters
and it and it's been lost in the public
realm that's the kind of point and the
language of the spiritual is a way of
saying Luke C give your fundamental
questions of what I call in the book
love death self and soul which is you
know think of questions of being
becoming beyond this yeah and I forget
what the fourth one is but anyway the
thing is these fundamental processes in
life and where are we with them they
were not going to resolve that we're not
gonna like say okay here's the meaning
of life and therefore we live like this
but we do have to structure society in a
way that is responding to ultimate
questions of meaning and purpose the
part of the problem with liberalism and
I was I still I have a functional
liberal by the way it's not as though
you know I still love the freedom that
liberalism is conferred I'm just
becoming more aware of its cause well
it's cost is a kind of superficiality
where you're you don't meditate on on
death for example I don't mean to be
heavy but you know we're in a situation
right now where a lot of our elders are
gonna die I'm sorry it just keeps coming
up because there's a subtext to all
these things you're talking about it is
it is except it's much smaller than a
doctrine it's tiny micro particles that
are causing the problem and right so the
virus so the president macro and last
night I just told us that we're at war
against at the virus so first of all I
thought oh Jesus Christ it's like are
you trying to be like de Gaulle or
something and using this outdated
rhetoric I think that the whole system
is so stupid are on a spiritual level
right right I mean we're at war against
the virus it seems to me the opposite is
true where we're gonna have to figure
out how to make peaceful opera make
peace with each other
right away but well I'm sorry for the
rant but that's okay that's okay let u
s-- plan it's a difficult one for many
reasons but I mean there's a lot going
on right so there's there's perfect
Eva's why they want to loop it back best
way of doing this one of your previous
discussions with Zack I believe he spoke
a little bit about the educational
meta-crisis yeah and he spoke a little
bit about forming questions he feels
that our defining of our time so the
kind of meta-crisis distilled of the
four questions those are very much
haters but they partly came about
through conversations we we'd had and
four questions really are what's going
on roughly which is a question of sense
making or intelligibility is a question
of are we up to it which is basically
about capability then there's like who's
in charge and who gets to decide which
is a question of legitimacy or Zack
calls of legitimation sometimes quoting
Hamas and then finally there's kind of
meaning or what's it all about what are
we trying to do these four questions
going to be superimposed on the virus
sure do you want to go through them joy
yeah that's it
so I would say the intelligibility
question what's going on is that we're
doing that work reasonably well as a
species I think it could be better but
there is a great deal of sense making
going on and the challenge is not to
rush to judgment about what is a good
and bad response but nonetheless the
problem there is while you're making
sense of things what do you do right you
can't wait for a month to figure out get
all the dates that you need to make the
fully informed judgment you have to make
a decision often with incomplete
knowledge in the context of uncertainty
yeah there the question is that comes
into a question of underlying values I
would say the first instinct should be
care in the first instance should be
kind of Caritas rather than Veritas you
know it's like
protect what you love and then figure
out what the attack is what the threat
is
so personally I think very early on when
it became clear this was a new kind of
infectious disease a virus that was
fatal for a small percentage of the
population that would grow exponentially
over time because of the early
patterning of increase over weeks they
missed the axis exponential curve kind
of I think while they were able to deal
with that yeah I didn't miss it or they
didn't know what it meant or but I think
rather than waiting to make perfect
sense mmm what's way on here is highly
Hugh how does a human species as a whole
deal with conditions of an epistemic
uncertainty where we're still looking to
authority to tell us what's going on
what do we do but we can't do that
really we can to some extent defer to
experts the son extent look for the most
reliable sources but we still have to
figure out for ourselves do I send my
school son to school tomorrow or not
yeah and do I do I go shopping once a
week is that safe or should I wait until
you know who knows till it's all cleared
up and these questions are ultimately
ours to answer but they arise from the
question to crisis of intelligibility of
not knowing what's going on yes that's -
at the time of the virus but it's there
all the time they're all the time very
interesting yeah that's the first thing
the second thing is on capability
there's real questions here but are we
up to at night there's some really good
stories here about capability because
with 3d machines and be mobilised to
create new kinds of medical equipment
that that wouldn't have been possible a
long time ago there are some signs that
vaccination efforts are being
accelerated yeah already some evidence
about things that we can take to reduce
the chance of fatality if you catch it
so as not as of the human species is not
mobilizing the capability response sure
anyways we are up to this we're also
planning carefully to flatten the curve
and reduce impacts and hospitals and all
that but it begs the question of more
generally our wisdom
yeah oh yeah we're not a wisdom yet okay
that was one of my questions for you
okay keep if you know my PhD wasn't with
them so yeah I've come to that but I'm
on the context in the context of the
virus the capability question is are we
up to dealing with this in a way that
minimizes harm now that's not just about
the medical response it's also about the
social and civic society response yes
for example enlightened governments from
now be doing things like giving a
temporary universal basic income to
everyone so that there's not people are
not going to work and getting infected
or going schooling getting infected
because they have to pay their bills
right yeah now you need to take that
problem out of the equation so there's a
key the ability question that's
heightened are we up to it yeah are we
gonna leave a lot of people behind even
if we solve the problem you know people
who can't afford to pay the bills after
you know after losing their their job
that comes for the next bit legitimacy
because there are justice questions and
fairness questions the question of
legitimacy looms large here because it's
about who gets to decide who lives and
dies on what basis right so the UK
government for example appeared to make
a decision that would would put the
elders especially and follow the elders
run up in the elderly because mmm the
elders yeah I think we need to talk
about the elders I'm just gonna bracket
that because they're not the elderly
there are the elders that the history of
our civilization right right that
contain the knowledge I mean totally
looking at older people as elders you
know really and yeah there there's some
things described in a sort of sense that
would make it look like they were
dispensable indeed yeah and the same
with underlying conditions you know we
use that term as if oh the RET were
already somehow halfway gone but
actually no I haven't I'm type 1
diabetic I have an underlying condition
I know many of my family does too and so
this virus isn't real and present danger
to lots of people and governments are
making decisions that will have very
direct bearing
humans and diets that's a legitimacy
question and it's heightened right again
and then finally the meeting crisis
which I'm sure will be the one that
interest you the most yeah there it's
the direct encounter with death right
yeah it's a by the time I use something
that I learned from a conversation with
we need to Roy I forget the precise
context but you know the idea that we
can prevent death doesn't really stack
up you know at some level we're all
altom utley gonna die yeah yes sir are
in some ways a scandalous open secret
that you know that we are so utterly
contingent so dependent on a beating
beating muscle that could stop beating
at almost any time so what the virus
does it again heightens that experience
suddenly it's like hang on I didn't
think my life was a question work but
the virus says it might be right yeah
it's a kind of scandal also a moment of
reckoning and one of the reasons your
life is at risk is that the global
system is so thoroughly interdependent
and fragile really fragile even if you
can show data showing enormous progress
on literacy and medical and scientific
advances and even prosperity and people
coming out of poverty and young kids
learning to read and African nations
getting better you can tell an
optimistic story of civilization yeah
that deeper will often obscure the
underlying agility of the system right
which is about a function of
interdependence and a function of
complex systems only requiring minor
changes to become to create macro read
your facts right and this makes me think
of your critique of our critique of
liberalism which tries to hide death at
any cost right yeah and I guess if you
were if you your wife is Indian people
who live in India they burned the corpse
you know in the open so there's a
meditation on death and it seems like
this virus I was thinking is forcing us
into a meditation on death
way you might like this so when I did
the spirituality project death was one
of the themes and the pieces research
that I was most taken by was related to
a phenomenon known as post-traumatic
growth yeah I mean murdered best right
post-traumatic stress everyone knows
about it's what military people come
back with and we have a control monster
and post-traumatic growth is very
different than others it's often people
who were close to death who may have had
cancer or may have had an accident
yeah and they survived it and then
they're like okay what was I doing all
that time given them a given that I now
know my life is so fragile I think a
little bit differently and what what the
research shows is those who have
near-death experiences not so much in
this spiritual I was looking at my body
from above way but more the kind of I
almost died and I'm not sure I looked
like I want to live way yeah if you have
that experience what research shows is
people invariably turn towards a life of
more intrinsic value closer connection
to nature and loved ones their own
crafts and pursuits much less concerned
for status much less concerned for
achievement and but use the the killer
you think that I find very curious about
that it comes about because people
realize they almost stopped it and they
were going to die yeah but they knew
that already right yeah this is the
thing that's very bizarre is as if the
human being well we know it
intellectually but we don't have a
direct encounter with with with it or or
are able we're not able to digest it or
feel it in a full-on way and once we do
Wow
we wake up you know right so I guess one
thing is one way of seeing the virus is
it's a species wide encounter with our
individual and shared mortality mm-hmm
and that's uh that could be ultimately a
positive thing although there will be a
lot of tragedy and a lot of heartache
and pain and literal asphyxiation along
the way so
yeah it's dark and it's a moment of
reckoning it's also something that may
pass and be forgotten within six months
yeah but I don't sense that at the
moment but it's possible part of the
offense making me part of the
intelligibility aspect I mentioned
earlier is we don't know how long this
is gonna last and that's an unusual
situation we have this feeling that
there is a normal reality we have to get
back to I think what this shows is that
that normal reality was a kind of
fiction yeah the normal reality is a
fiction and everything's going to change
on some level even if everything appears
to be somewhat the same it seems like
there has to be some kind of wide
systemic change after this it's just
there's just no question about that well
well hold on many I'm being too
optimistic well if we could go back to
being the same idiots that we were you
know always but we have immunity to
change you know Robert Keegan absolutely
this and I wouldn't be surprised how
quickly we can hide this under the
carpet as a word and get about a
business but one we have seen this to
bring it back to a more religious
sensibility if this is a moment of
profound deceitful Abril mm-hmm yeah if
our habit energy and our main patterns
Society at a societal level or by going
through the motions this is a moment
where we're not allowed to go through
the motions we have to change how we
live and think and act and reflect and
what that reminds me of is why Jesus
used parables right mm-hmm and it seems
like a different world but actually has
a connection so the connection with
Jesus's and parables I'd say is this
going into the historical context he was
in there are some people who believe
that is not the Jesus studied PHP as
such but he sort of recognized that
there was something as they recognized
if this is Gotham those languages of
Europe spirit but there was something
about the person as teacher a spiritual
teacher that he realized that in his
heavily historically
loaded time or you have the Romans and
you're the Pharisees and you have the
practices and the ritual purity and
who's meant to be a messiah and who's
meant to be a rabbi it comes into all of
that context and he doesn't see I am
this and this is why things are
he tells lots and lots of stories mm-hmm
yeah why would he do that right and the
claim is at least in some of the
research like in Zen
they do the same thing they right it's a
little bit like the coins right yeah
these crazy deliberately creating new
cycle Librium because only in that face
of disequilibrium can some new
understanding emerge some new cell
emerge some new society emerge right
good see the viruses are kind of opening
up that this equilibrium allowing us the
time to reflect and withdraw and
hopefully transform in some way yeah
yeah I imagine oh be both I mean for
some people will go just nuts and then
other people will will go you know it's
a chance to actually go and retreat like
seems to me like I don't know as a
practicing Buddhist for 20 years going
on retreat is something where you
actually go deeper into life you know
it's not an escape from life it's
actually you go deeper into life and and
it's a chance to do that yeah yeah so I
mean I fear people for 70 who did who
might be relatively lucky in this regard
I think for others you've got cramped
living quarters
exactly going up domestic violence you
have you know there are other ways of
telling the story oh but I mean
certainly in principle it affords that
opportunity
amongst other things yeah yeah I mean
you're right to mention that it could
just people could retreat into their
hell all right whereas they might have
had a way out before yeah so so it's
it's you know it's both things